Guide to the Dorothea Lynde Dix papers, 1862-1880s and undated. RL.10408
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Dorothea Lynde Dix papers
1862-1880s and undated.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Dix, Dorothea Lynde, 1802-1887
RL.10408
0.1 Linear Feet 1 folder
Dorothea Dix was an American author, teacher, and reformer who advocated for improving treatment and facilities for mental health care. She also served as a superintendent for women nurses during the American Civil War. This collection consists of assorted pieces of correspondence and poetry by Dix, many relating to her health, treatment of patients, and other personal topics. Includes a 1862 letter signed by Abraham Lincoln relaying her recommendations to Edwin Stanton.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
Some materials acquired through a purchase from Schuman's book dealer, date unknown. One item (letter to Mrs. Page) acquired through a donation from Carolyn J. Porter in 1935. Accession 2022-0155 acquired through a purchase from William Reese Company.
Historical Note
Dorothea Lynde Dix (1802-1887) was an American author, teacher, and reformer who advocated for improving treatment and facilities for mental health care. She also served as a superintendent for nurses during the American Civil War.
Dix was originally from Hampden, Maine and attended school in Boston, Mass. She became interested in mental healthcare while living abroad in Europe, and returned to the United States to tour American facilities. She publicly advocated for the cause, lobbying healthcare officers and politicians, and raising funds through state allocations and private contributions to improve hospitals and medical treatment of mental health patients throughout the country. Her work led to the establishment of state asylums in North Carolina, New Jersey, and Illinois.
During the American Civil War, Dix was designated as Superintendent of Army Nurses for the Union Army. She sought formal training and opportunities for women in nursing, and over the course of the war appointed over 3000 nurses. She later fundraised for a national monument for deceased soldiers, now standing at Fort Monroe, Virginia.
Dix had recurring health problems throughout her life, and spent later years as a resident of the New Jersey State Hospital in Trenton.
Source: Norwood, Arlisha R. "Dorothea Dix," National Women's History Museum website, accessed 2022 Nov. 10: https://www.womenshistory.org/education-resources/biographies/dorothea-dix
Collection Overview
This collection consists of assembled and acquired examples of correspondence and poetry written by Dorothea Dix. Some materials date from the 1860s. In one note, dated May 1862, Dix lists recommendations for promotions in the US Army hospital administration. This bears an autograph note, signed by Abraham Lincoln, forwarding the list for consideration to Secretary of War Stanton.
Other letters date from the 1870s and 1880s and relate friends of Dix or to Dix's own care and health, particularly regarding her residency at a State Hospital in Trenton, near Philadelphia. Dix occasionally references her work for mentally ill patients.
The collection also contains two poems; one signed D.L.D. and another attributed to Dix.
Mental health; American poetry -- Women authors; American Civil War (1861-1865); Psychiatric hospitals -- United States; Philanthropists -- United States -- Correspondence; Women in charitable work -- United States; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865
- "Thou Shalt Reap if Thou Not Faint" manuscript poem, signed D.L.D., approximately 1880s (Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  A typed transcription of this poem is included in the folder.
- "Nursing and Watching" manuscript poem, signed W., approximately 1880s (Folder 1)
- Note from Dix nominating physicians for different Army hospital positions, also signed by Abraham Lincoln, 1862 May 5 (Folder 1)
  Item is a note in Dix's hand with different physician recommendations for staffing medical positions. At the end of her text is a manuscript note: "Sec. of War please give fair and respectful consideration to the within recommendations of Miss Dix. A. Lincoln, May 5, 1862."
- Letter from D.L. Dix to unknown Sir, asking for a contribution for wounded soldiers, on Office of Women Nurses, U.S. Hospital Service letterhead, 1865 April 7 (Folder 1)
  Includes a concluding comment from Dix: "What glorious news!!" presumably referring to the surrender of the Confederacy.
- Letter from D.L. Dix, at the Library of Congress, asking to meet with Mr. Stewart about "the interests of certain Superintendents of Hospitals", 1869 Jan. 30 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Dix to unknown recipient, Library, Pennsylvania, approximately 1870s-1880s (Folder 1)
  Letter signed D.L. Dix regarding a bill from Dr. Kirkbride as well as Mrs. Lanson who "is very insane - and asking advice concerning a Hospital less expensive than that at Phila."
- Letter from D.L. Dix to Anna M. Price, Bulfinch Place, approximately 1870s-1880s (Folder 1)
  Dix writes to inspire and encourage Price in her pursuit of teaching; letter includes scripture quotations. At the conclusion of the letter, Dix notes that "I am at present something indisposed, but hope to recover strength."
- Letter from Dix to Mrs. Nichols, Morris Plains, 1880 Dec. 27 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Dix, Trenton, to Mrs. Beulah M. Hacker (Woodside), Germantown (Phil.), Pa., 1882 Dec. 24 (Folder 1)
  Dix thanks her friend for a sympathy card while she is receiving care for poor health.
- Letter from D.L.D. to Mrs. Page, 1887 May 3-4 (Folder 1)
  Dix thanks Mrs. Page for her letter, and writes about her current poor health and situation as a resident at the State Hospital. She praises her useful nurse: "I think your experience will have realized how very few are to be found who are real nurses - many have acquired by teaching what supplies 'certificates' of ability - but no certificate represents the truly reliable nurse." Dix continues the letter on May 4 with details about her diagnosis: "Ossification of the lining membranes of the arteries." She writes that she feels ill but that her reason was "at no time threatened." A typed transcription of this letter is also included in the folder.